Today I want to tell you
أرغب اليوم في أن أخبركم
about a project being carried out
عن مشروع يشارك فيه
by scientists all over the world
العديد من العلماء من مختلف أنحاء العالم
to paint a neural portrait of the human mind.
لرسم صورة عصبية للعقل البشريّ.
And the central idea of this work
الفكرة المركزية وراء هذا المشروع
is that the human mind and brain
هي أنّ العقل والدماغ البشريّ
is not a single, general-purpose processor,
هو ليس معالج معلومات أحاديّا عامّا
but a collection of highly specialized components,
بل هو مجموعة من المكونات المحدّدة بدقّة
each solving a different specific problem,
كل منها له دوره الخاص
and yet collectively making up
لكنها تشكّل معا في نفس الوقت
who we are as human beings and thinkers.
هويتّنا كبشر مفكّرين.
To give you a feel for this idea,
لإعطائك نبذة عن تلك الفكرة،
imagine the following scenario:
تخيّل السيناريو التّالي:
You walk into your child's day care center.
دخلت لتوّك حضانة الأطفال حيث يوجد أحد أطفالك
As usual, there's a dozen kids there
وكالعادة، هناك عشرات من الأطفال هناك
waiting to get picked up,
بانتظار آبائهم
but this time,
لكنك هذه المرّة
the children's faces look weirdly similar,
تحسّ وكأن وجوه جميع الأطفال مألوفة
and you can't figure out which child is yours.
ولا تستطيع تمييز أيّهم هو طفلك.
Do you need new glasses?
هل تحتاج نظارات جديدة؟
Are you losing your mind?
هل أنت بصدد فقدان عقلك؟
You run through a quick mental checklist.
تحاول تفقّد قدراتك الذهنية،
No, you seem to be thinking clearly,
لا، أنت تفكّر جيدا وبطريقة عادية
and your vision is perfectly sharp.
ونظرك لا يزال حادّا كالعادة
And everything looks normal
وكلّ شيء يبدو عاديّا
except the children's faces.
باستثناء وجوه الأطفال.
You can see the faces,
تستطيع رؤية الوجوه
but they don't look distinctive,
لكنّها لا تبدو مميّزة
and none of them looks familiar,
ولا أحد منها يبدو مألوفا
and it's only by spotting an orange hair ribbon
ولولا رؤية أشرطة الشعر البرتقالية
that you find your daughter.
لما تعرّفت على ابنتك.
This sudden loss of the ability to recognize faces
هذا الفقدان المفاجئ لقدرة تمييز الوجوه
actually happens to people.
يحدث فعلا للأشخاص.
It's called prosopagnosia,
ويسمّى "عمى التعرّف على الوجوه"
and it results from damage
وهو نتيجة تلف
to a particular part of the brain.
لمنطقة محدّدة من الدماغ.
The striking thing about it
الأمر المذهل هو أنّ
is that only face recognition is impaired;
التعرّف على الوجوه فقط يتعطّل
everything else is just fine.
بينما بقية الوظائف بخير.
Prosopagnosia is one of many surprisingly specific
عمى التعرّف على الوجوه هو من أكثر الإعاقات
mental deficits that can happen after brain damage.
الذهنية غرابة التي يمكن أن تحدث نتيجة تضرّر الدماغ.
These syndromes collectively
هذه المتلازمات مجتمعة
have suggested for a long time
كانت تشير منذ وقت طويل إلى كون
that the mind is divvied up into distinct components,
العقل منقسما إلى عناصر منفصلة،
but the effort to discover those components
لكن محاولات اكتشاف هذه العناصر
has jumped to warp speed
تزايدت بشكل ملحوظ منذ
with the invention of brain imaging technology,
اختراع تكنولوجيا التصوير الدماغي وخاصة
especially MRI.
التصوير بالرنين المغناطيسي.
So MRI enables you to see internal anatomy
إذ أنّه يمكّن من رؤية التركيبة الداخلية
at high resolution,
بدرجة عالية من الوضوح.
so I'm going to show you in a second
سوف أريكم بعد قليل
a set of MRI cross-sectional images
مجموعة من صور مقطعية بالرنين المغناطيسي
through a familiar object,
لأمر مألوف وسوف
and we're going to fly through them
نسافر عبر الصور
and you're going to try to figure out what the object is.
محاولين معرفة ما هو هذا الشيء.
Here we go.
لنبدأ.
It's not that easy. It's an artichoke.
ليس سهلا، إنّه خرشوف.
Okay, let's try another one,
حسنا، لنجرّب مرة أخرى،
starting from the bottom and going through the top.
بدء من الأسفل وصعودا إلى أعلى
Broccoli! It's a head of broccoli.
القرنبيط! رأس القرنبيط
Isn't it beautiful? I love that.
أليس جميلا؟ أحبه
Okay, here's another one. It's a brain, of course.
هذا آخر، إنّه دماغ بالطبع
In fact, it's my brain.
دماغي في الواقع
We're going through slices through my head like that.
سوف نمرّ خلال رأسي عبر شرائح هكذا
That's my nose over on the right, and now
هذا أنفي إلى اليمين، والآن
we're going over here, right there.
سوف نذهب هنا، هناك تماما
So this picture's nice, if I do say so myself,
الصورة جميلة، وهو أيضا رأيي الشخصي
but it shows only anatomy.
لكنها ترينا التشريح فقط.
The really cool advance with functional imaging
التطور المثير في التصوير الوظيفيّ
happened when scientists figured out how to make
حدث عندما اكتشف العلماء كيفية صنع
pictures that show not just anatomy but activity,
صور لا تكشف التشريح فقط بل النشاط أيضا
that is, where neurons are firing.
أي عندما تعمل الخلايا العصبية.
So here's how this works.
إليكم كيف يعمل الأمر
Brains are like muscles.
الأدمغة هي أشبه بعضلات
When they get active,
عندما تصبح نشطة،
they need increased blood flow to supply that activity,
تحتاج إلى ازدياد تدفّق الدم للتزود من أجل ذلك النشاط
and lucky for us, blood flow control to the brain is local,
ومن حسن حظنا، التحكم بتدفق الدم في الدم موجود قريبا
so if a bunch of neurons, say, right there
إن رغبت مجموعة من الخلايا العصبية
get active and start firing,
في العمل والإرسال،
then blood flow increases just right there.
يزداد تدفق الدم هناك بالذات
So functional MRI picks up on that blood flow increase,
يلتقط التصوير بالرنين المغناطيسي الوظيفي ذلك الارتفاع في ضغط الدم
producing a higher MRI response
منتجا استجابة رنين مغناطيسي أفضل
where neural activity goes up.
عند ارتفاع النشاط العصبي.
So to give you a concrete feel
لإعطائكم فكرة واقعية عن كيفية حدوث
for how a functional MRI experiment goes
تجربة التصوير بالرنين المغناطيسي الوظيفي
and what you can learn from it
وما نتعلمه عنها
and what you can't,
أو لا نتعلمه عنها
let me describe one of the first studies I ever did.
دعوني أصف إحدى أولى دراسات على الإطلاق
We wanted to know if there was a special part of the brain for recognizing faces,
أردنا معرفة إن كانت هناك منطقة من الدماغ وظيفتها تمييز الوجوه
and there was already reason to think there might be such a thing
وكان هناك ما يدعونا للاعتقاد بذلك
based on this phenomenon of prosopagnosia
اعتمادا على ظاهرة عمى تعرّف الوجوه
that I described a moment ago,
التي وصفتها منذ قليل
but nobody had ever seen that part of the brain
لكن ما من أحد أجد ذلك الجزء من الدماغ
in a normal person,
في شخص عادي
so we set out to look for it.
لذلك قررنا البحث عنه.
So I was the first subject.
كنت أنا أولى المجربين
I went into the scanner, I lay on my back,
ذهبت للماسح، استلقيت على ظهري،
I held my head as still as I could
أبقيت رأسي ثابتا لأطول مدة ممكنة
while staring at pictures of faces like these
أثناء مشاهدة صور لوجوه هكذا
and objects like these
وأشياء كهذه
and faces and objects for hours.
وجوها وأشياء لساعات.
So as somebody who has pretty close to the world record
كشخص يقترب من تحطيم الرقم القياسي لعدد الساعات
of total number of hours spent inside an MRI scanner,
المقضية داخل ماسح التصوير بالرنين المغناطيسي،
I can tell you that one of the skills
أخبركم أن إحدى المهارات
that's really important for MRI research
الهامة جدا أثناء القيام بذلك
is bladder control.
هي حبس البول.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
When I got out of the scanner,
عند خروجي من الماسح
I did a quick analysis of the data,
قمت بتحليل سريع للبيانات
looking for any parts of my brain
بحثا عن أيّ أجزاء من دماغي
that produced a higher response when I was looking at faces
ولّدت استجابة أقوى عند رؤيتي للوجوه
than when I was looking at objects,
مقارنة بعند رؤيتي للأشياء
and here's what I saw.
وهذا ما رأيته.
Now this image looks just awful by today's standards,
هذه الصورة تبدو سيئة مقارنة بالمعايير الحالية
but at the time I thought it was beautiful.
لكنها بدت لي جميلة في ذلك الوقت.
What it shows is that region right there,
وهي ترينا أنّ المنطقة هنا تماما
that little blob,
تلك النقطة الصغيرة
it's about the size of an olive
في حجم حبة زيتون تقريبا
and it's on the bottom surface of my brain
وهي في أسفل سطح دماغي
about an inch straight in from right there.
بعيدة إنشا واحدا تقريبا عن هنا
And what that part of my brain is doing
ما تقوم به تلك المنطقة من الدماغ
is producing a higher MRI response,
يولّد استجابة رنين مغناطيسي أقوى
that is, higher neural activity,
يعني، هناك نشاط عصبي أقوى
when I was looking at faces
عند رؤيتي للوجوه
than when I was looking at objects.
مقارنة بوقت رؤيتي للأجسام.
So that's pretty cool,
الأمر رائع
but how do we know this isn't a fluke?
لكن كيف نعرف أنّها ليست ضربة حظ؟
Well, the easiest way
الطريقة الأسهل هي
is to just do the experiment again.
بالقيام بالتجربة مجددا.
So I got back in the scanner,
إذن عدت للماسح
I looked at more faces and I looked at more objects
ونظرت لوجوه أكثر وأشياء أكثر
and I got a similar blob,
وحصلت على نفس النتيجة
and then I did it again
ثم كررت الأمر
and I did it again
وأعدتها مجددا
and again and again,
ومجددا ومجددا
and around about then
عندها فقط
I decided to believe it was for real.
بدأت أصدّق أنّ الأمر صحيح.
But still, maybe this is something weird about my brain
لكن ربما هو أمر مرتبط بدماغي أنا فقط
and no one else has one of these things in there,
وما من أحد له نفس الأمر
so to find out, we scanned a bunch of other people
وللتأكد، قمنا بمسح أدمغة أشخاص آخرين
and found that pretty much everyone
واكتشفنا أنّ جميعهم يمتلكون
has that little face-processing region
تلك المنطقة الخاصة بتمييز الوجوه
in a similar neighborhood of the brain.
في مكان مماثل بأدمغتهم.
So the next question was,
السؤال الذي طرح بعد ذلك هو
what does this thing really do?
ماهي فعلا وظيفة ذلك الشيء؟
Is it really specialized just for face recognition?
هل هو فعلا مخصّص فقط لتمييز الوجوه؟
Well, maybe not, right?
ربّما لا،
Maybe it responds not only to faces
ربما لا يستجيب للوجوه فقط
but to any body part.
بل لبقية أعضاء الجسم أيضا
Maybe it responds to anything human
ربما يستجيب لأي شيء بشريّ
or anything alive
أو أي كائن حيّ
or anything round.
أو أي شيء دائري.
The only way to be really sure that that region
الطريقة الوحيدة للتأكد أنّ تلك المنطقة
is specialized for face recognition
مسؤولة فقط عن تمييز الوجوه
is to rule out all of those hypotheses.
هي عبر دحض تلك الافتراضات.
So we spent much of the next couple of years
لذلك قضينا الكثير من وقتنا في السنوات اللاحقة
scanning subjects while they looked at lots
نمسح أدمغة أشخاص أثناء
of different kinds of images,
نظرهم لمختلف أنواع الصور
and we showed that that part of the brain
وكشفنا أنّ ذلك الجزء من الدماغ
responds strongly when you look at
يستجيب بقوة عند نظرك إلى أي صورة
any images that are faces of any kind,
لأيّ نوع من أنواع الوجوه
and it responds much less strongly
ويستجيب بصفة أقل بكثير
to any image you show that isn't a face,
لأي صورة ليست لوجه
like some of these.
مثل هذه.
So have we finally nailed the case
إذن، هل تأكدنا نهائيا
that this region is necessary for face recognition?
من كون تلك المنطقة ضرورية لتمييز الوجوه؟
No, we haven't.
لا، ليس بعد.
Brain imaging can never tell you
التصوير الدماغي غير قادر على إخبارنا
if a region is necessary for anything.
إن كانت منطقة ما ضرورية لوظيفة ما.
All you can do with brain imaging
ما يمكنك فعله بالتصوير الدماغي
is watch regions turn on and off
هو مشاهدة المناطق تعمل وتتوقف عن العمل
as people think different thoughts.
أثناء تفكير الأشخاص بمختلف الأمور.
To tell if a part of the brain is necessary for a mental function,
لمعرفة ما إن كانت منطقة ما ضرورية لوظيفة ذهنية،
you need to mess with it and see what happens,
تحتاج للعبث بها وترقّب النتيجة
and normally we don't get to do that.
لكننا لا نستطيع القيام بذلك عادة.
But an amazing opportunity came about
لكن فرصة مميزة ظهرت
very recently when a couple of colleagues of mine
مؤخّرا عندما قام بعض زملائي
tested this man who has epilepsy
باختبار شخص مصاب بداء الصرع
and who is shown here in his hospital bed
ترونه هنا مستلقيا بالمستشفى
where he's just had electrodes placed
حيث تمّ وضع أقطاب كهربائية
on the surface of his brain
على سطح دماغه
to identify the source of his seizures.
لمعرفة مصدر نوبات صرعه.
So it turned out by total chance
وبالصدفة، تبيّن أنّ
that two of the electrodes
القطبين الكهربائيين
happened to be right on top of his face area.
كانا موجودين في منطقة فوق رأسه تماما.
So with the patient's consent,
إذن وبموافقة المريض،
the doctors asked him what happened
سأله الأطباء عمّا حدث
when they electrically stimulated that part of his brain.
عندما قاموا بتحفيز تلك المنطقة من الدماغ.
Now, the patient doesn't know
المريض لم يكن يعلم
where those electrodes are,
مكان الأقطاب الكهربائية
and he's never heard of the face area.
ولم يسبق له أن سمع بمنطقة الوجه بالدماغ.
So let's watch what happens.
لنشاهد ما حدث.
It's going to start with a control condition
سيبدأ الأمر بظروف تحت السيطرة
that will say "Sham" nearly invisibly
حيث تظهر كلمة "شام" شبه متخفية
in red in the lower left,
بالأحمر بأسفل الشمال
when no current is delivered,
حيث لا يوجد تيار كهربائي
and you'll hear the neurologist speaking to the patient first. So let's watch.
وستسمعون طبيب الأعصاب يتحدث مع المصاب أولا. لنرى.
(Video) Neurologist: Okay, just look at my face
(فيديو) طبيب الأعصاب: حسنا، انظر إلى وجهي
and tell me what happens when I do this.
وأخبرني عمّا يحدث عندما أفعل هذا
All right?
حسنا؟
Patient: Okay.
المصاب: حسنا.
Neurologist: One, two, three.
الطبيب: واحد، اثنان، ثلاثة
Patient: Nothing. Neurologist: Nothing? Okay.
المصاب: لا شيء الطبيب: لا شيء؟ حسنا.
I'm going to do it one more time.
سأقوم مجددا بالأمر
Look at my face.
انظر إلى وجهي
One, two, three.
واحد، اثنان، ثلاثة
Patient: You just turned into somebody else.
المصاب: لقد تحوّلت إلى شخص آخر
Your face metamorphosed.
لقد تغيّر وجهك
Your nose got saggy, it went to the left.
أنفك أصبح أكبر، ومتجّها نحو الأيسر
You almost looked like somebody I'd seen before,
تبدو تقريبا كشخص مألوف لي
but somebody different.
لكنك شخص مختلف.
That was a trip.
يا لها من رحلة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Nancy Kanwisher: So this experiment —
نانسي كانويشر: هذه التجربة —
(Applause) —
(تصفيق)
this experiment finally nails the case
هذه التجربة تؤكد أخيرا الاعتقاد
that this region of the brain is not only
بكون هذه المنطقة من الدماغ ليست فقط
selectively responsive to faces
تستجيب للوجوه بطريقة مختارة
but causally involved in face perception.
لكنها تتدخّل في رؤية الوجوه.
So I went through all of these details
لقد مررت بكل هذه التفاصيل
about the face region to show you what it takes
لأكشف لكم ما يتطلّبه الأمر
to really establish that a part of the brain
قبل الإقرار بأنّ منطقة من الدماغ
is selectively involved in a specific mental process.
هي بالفعل مسؤولة عن وظيفة ذهنية معيّنة.
Next, I'll go through much more quickly
الآن سوف أمرّ بطريقة أسرع
some of the other specialized regions of the brain
ببعض المناطق الأخرى من الدماغ
that we and others have found.
التي اكتشفتها أنا وغيري.
So to do this, I've spent a lot of time
للقيام بذلك، قضيت الكثير من الوقت
in the scanner over the last month
في الماسح أثناء الشهر المنصرم
so I can show you these things in my brain.
حتّى أريكم هذه الأشياء بدماغي.
So let's get started. Here's my right hemisphere.
لنبدأ. هذا نصف الكرة المخية اليمنى الخاص بي
So we're oriented like that. You're looking at my head this way.
نحن ننظر بهذا الاتجاه. أنتم تنظرون لرأسي هكذا.
Imagine taking the skull off
تخيّل نزع الجمجمة
and looking at the surface of the brain like that.
والنظر إلى سطح الدماغ هكذا.
Okay, now as you can see,
الآن يمكنكم رؤية
the surface of the brain is all folded up.
سطح الدماغ مطويّ، وهذا سيء
So that's not good. Stuff could be hidden in there.
يمكن لأشياء أن تكون مختفية هناك
We want to see the whole thing,
نريد رؤية الكل
so let's inflate it so we can see the whole thing.
دعونا إذن نضخّم، كي نرى الأمر كله
Next, let's find that face area I've been talking about
لنبحث عن تلك المنطقة التي تحدّثت عنها
that responds to images like these.
التي تستجيب لصور من هذا النوع.
To see that, let's turn the brain around
لرؤية ذلك، لنقلب الدماغ
and look on the inside surface on the bottom,
وننظر إلى الجهة الباطنية في الأسفل
and there it is, that's my face area.
ها هي، تلك هي منطقة الوجه خاصتي
Just to the right of that is another region
على يمينها مباشرة هناك منطقة أخرى
that is shown in purple
لونها بنفسجي هنا
that responds when you process color information,
تستجيب عند استيعابك لمعلومات عن الألوان
and near those regions are other regions
وجانبها مناطق أخرى
that are involved in perceiving places,
تتدخّل في رؤية الأماكن
like right now, I'm seeing this layout of space around me
الآن مثلا، أنا أرى هذا التصميم الفضائي حولي
and these regions in green right there
والمناطق الخضراء هنا
are really active.
هي في الواقع نشطة.
There's another one out on the outside surface again
هذه أخرى لكنها على السطح أيضا
where there's a couple more face regions as well.
حيث يوجد مزيد من مناطق الوجه.
Also in this vicinity
أيضا في الجوار هناك
is a region that's selectively involved
منطقة تتدخّل انتقائيا
in processing visual motion,
في عملية الابصار الحركي
like these moving dots here,
كهذه النقاط المتحركة هنا
and that's in yellow at the bottom of the brain,
واللون الأصفر أسفل الدماغ
and near that is a region that responds
وقريبا هناك منطقة تستجيب
when you look at images of bodies and body parts
عند نظرك نحو صور للجسم أو أعضائه
like these, and that region is shown in lime green
كهذه، وتلك المنطقة بالأخضر الباهت
at the bottom of the brain.
أسفل الدماغ.
Now all these regions I've shown you so far
كل هذه المناطق التي أريتكم إياها لحدّ الآن
are involved in specific aspects of visual perception.
مسؤولة عن أشكال من الإبصار.
Do we also have specialized brain regions
هل لدينا أيضا مناطق دماغية
for other senses, like hearing?
مخصصة لحواس أخرى كالسمع؟
Yes, we do. So if we turn the brain around a little bit,
نعم، إذا قمنا بإدارة الدماغ قليلا
here's a region in dark blue
هذه المنطقة بالأزرق الداكن
that we reported just a couple of months ago,
التي قمنا بتقرير حولها منذ أشهر
and this region responds strongly
وهي تستجيب بقوة
when you hear sounds with pitch, like these.
عند سماعك لأصوات حادة هكذا
(Sirens)
(صفارة إنذار)
(Cello music)
(آلة تشيلو)
(Doorbell)
(جرس باب)
In contrast, that same region does not respond strongly
في المقابل، نفس الجهة لا تستجيب بقوة
when you hear perfectly familiar sounds
عند سماع أصوات مألوفة
that don't have a clear pitch, like these.
ليست لها نغمة واضحة كهذه
(Chomping)
(صوت قضم)
(Drum roll)
(دوران طبل)
(Toilet flushing)
(مياه الحمام)
Okay. Next to the pitch region
قرب منطقة الأنغام
is another set of regions that are selectively responsive
هناك مجموعة أخرى من المناطق التي تستجيب انتقائيا
when you hear the sounds of speech.
عند سماعك لأصوات الخطاب.
Okay, now let's look at these same regions.
الآن لننظر لنفس هذه المناطق
In my left hemisphere, there's a similar arrangement —
في الفص الدماغي الأيسر الخاص بي،
not identical, but similar —
هناك تشابه كبير
and most of the same regions are in here,
مع معظم نفس المناطق هنا
albeit sometimes different in size.
ولو كانت تختلف في الحجم.
Now, everything I've shown you so far
كلّ ما أريتكم إياه لحدّ الآن
are regions that are involved in different aspects of perception,
هي مناطق تتدخّل في أشكال مختلفة من الإبصار
vision and hearing.
السمع والرؤية.
Do we also have specialized brain regions
هل لدينا أيضا مناطق دماغية
for really fancy, complicated mental processes?
خاصة بوظائف ذهنية معقدة جدا؟
Yes, we do.
الإجابة هي نعم.
So here in pink are my language regions.
بالوردي مناطق دماغية خاصة باللغات
So it's been known for a very long time
من المعروف سابقا
that that general vicinity of the brain
أنّ المناطق المجاورة هنا
is involved in processing language,
تتدخّل في عملية استيعاب اللغات
but we showed very recently
وكشفنا في وقت ليس بالبعيد
that these pink regions
أنّ هذه المناطق الوردية
respond extremely selectively.
تستجيب بصفة انتقائية جدا.
They respond when you understand the meaning of a sentence,
تستجيب عند فهمك معنى جملة ما
but not when you do other complex mental things,
لكن لا تستجيب أثناء القيام بأنشطة ذهنية معقدّة
like mental arithmetic
مثل الحساب الذهني
or holding information in memory
أو حفظ معلومات بالذاكرة
or appreciating the complex structure
أو الإعجاب بالهيكلة المعقدة
in a piece of music.
لقطعة موسيقية.
The most amazing region that's been found yet
المنطقة الأكثر إثارة للإعجاب التي تمّ إيجادها لحدّ الآن
is this one right here in turquoise.
هي هذه باللون الأزرق الفيروزي.
This region responds
وهي تستجيب
when you think about what another person is thinking.
عندما تفكّر حول ما يفكّر فيه شخص آخر.
So that may seem crazy,
يبدو الأمر مجنونا
but actually, we humans do this all the time.
لكن في الواقع، كل البشر يقومون بذلك طيلة الوقت.
You're doing this when you realize
تقوم بذلك مثلا عندما تتفطّن إلى
that your partner is going to be worried
كون شريكك سوف يكون قلقا
if you don't call home to say you're running late.
إن لم تتصل بالمنزل لتعلم أنّك ستعود متأخرا.
I'm doing this with that region of my brain right now
أنا أقوم بذلك بتلك المنطقة من دماغي في هذه اللحظة
when I realize that you guys
عندما أتفطن إلى كونكم الآن
are probably now wondering about
على الأرجح تتساءلون
all that gray, uncharted territory in the brain,
عن ماهية تلك المناطق الدماغية
and what's up with that?
الملوّنة بالرماديّ والمجهولة.
Well, I'm wondering about that too,
أنا أيضا أتساءل نفس الشيء
and we're running a bunch of experiments in my lab right now
ونحن حاليا نجري مجموعة من التجارب في مختبري
to try to find a number of other
لمعرفة المزيد من التخصصات
possible specializations in the brain
الأخرى في الدماغ
for other very specific mental functions.
مرتبطة بوظائف ذهنية معينة.
But importantly, I don't think we have
لكن الأهم هو كوني لا أعتقد بامتلاكنا
specializations in the brain
تخصصات في الدماغ
for every important mental function,
لكل وظيفة ذهنية هامة،
even mental functions that may be critical for survival.
حتّى تلك التي قد تكون أساسية للبقاء.
In fact, a few years ago,
في الواقع، منذ بعض سنوات مضت،
there was a scientist in my lab
كان هناك عالم بمختبري
who became quite convinced
أصبح مقتنعا
that he'd found a brain region
أنّه قد يجد منطقة بالدماغ
for detecting food,
لكشف الطعام
and it responded really strongly in the scanner
تستجيب بقوة للماسح
when people looked at images like this.
عند نظر الأشخاص لصور هكذا.
And further, he found a similar response
لاحقا، اكتشف استجابة مماثلة
in more or less the same location
في نفس المنطقة تقريبا
in 10 out of 12 subjects.
في 10 على 12 من الأشخاص المشاركين.
So he was pretty stoked,
أحسّ بإثارة كبيرة
and he was running around the lab
ويجري في أنحاء المختبر
telling everyone that he was going to go on "Oprah"
مخبرا الجميع أنّه سيذهب لبرنامج "أوبرا"
with his big discovery.
بفضل اكتشافه العظيم.
But then he devised the critical test:
لكنه قام بتجربة هامة جدا:
He showed subjects images of food like this
جعل المشاركين يرون صورا لطعام هكذا
and compared them to images with very similar
وقارنها بصور ذات ألوان وأشكال
color and shape, but that weren't food, like these.
مشابهة جدا لكنها لم تكن لطعام، كهذه.
And his region responded the same
وتلك المنطقة استجابت بنفس
to both sets of images.
الطريقة لمجموعتي الصور.
So it wasn't a food area,
إذن هي ليست منطقة الطعام،
it was just a region that liked colors and shapes.
بل منطقة دماغية تحب الألوان والأشكال.
So much for "Oprah."
ما من ذهاب لأوبرا.
But then the question, of course, is,
لكن السؤال الذي يطرح هنا هو
how do we process all this other stuff
كيف نقوم بتحليل كل هذه الأشياء الأخرى
that we don't have specialized brain regions for?
التي ليس لدينا في أدمغتنا مناطق مخصصة بها؟
Well, I think the answer is that in addition
أظنّ أنّه إضافة
to these highly specialized components that I've been describing,
لكل تلك المكونات المخصصة التي تحدثت عنها،
we also have a lot of very general- purpose machinery in our heads
لدينا أيضا "آلات" شاملة الاختصاص في رؤوسنا
that enables us to tackle
تسمح لنا بحلّ
whatever problem comes along.
أي صعوبة قد تواجهنا.
In fact, we've shown recently that
في الواقع، كشفنا مؤخرا
these regions here in white
أنّ هذه المناطق هنا بالأبيض
respond whenever you do any difficult mental task
تستجيب كلما تقوم بأنشطة ذهنية صعبة
at all —
دائما —
well, of the seven that we've tested.
كالسبعة التي قمنا بتجربتها.
So each of the brain regions that I've described
كلّ من المناطق الدماغية التي تحدثت عنها
to you today
لكم اليوم
is present in approximately the same location
موجودة في نفس البقعة تقريبا
in every normal subject.
لكلّ شخص عادي.
I could take any of you,
يمكنني أخذ أي منكم
pop you in the scanner,
ووضعه تحت الماسح
and find each of those regions in your brain,
وإيجاد كل من هذه المناطق بدماغك
and it would look a lot like my brain,
وستكون مشابهة لتلك بدماغي
although the regions would be slightly different
رغم أنّها قد تكون مختلفة قليلا
in their exact location and in their size.
في مكانها بالضبط وحجمها.
What's important to me about this work
الأمر الأهم بالنسبة لي في هذا العمل
is not the particular locations of these brain regions,
ليس إيجاد المناطق الخاصة في الدماغ
but the simple fact that we have
بل حقيقة كوننا ببساطة
selective, specific components of mind and brain
نمتلك مكونات مخصصة وانتقائية
in the first place.
في دماغنا.
I mean, it could have been otherwise.
كان يمكن أن يكون الأمر مخالفا لذلك.
The brain could have been a single,
أن يكون الدماغ كتلة واحدة
general-purpose processor,
معالجة شاملة للمعلومات
more like a kitchen knife
أشبه بسكين مطبخ
than a Swiss Army knife.
عوض سكين سويسري متعدد الوظائف.
Instead, what brain imaging has delivered
عوض ذلك، فإنّ ما كشفه لنا التصوير الدماغي
is this rich and interesting picture of the human mind.
هو صورة ثرية ومثيرة للاهتمام عن العقل البشري.
So we have this picture of very general-purpose
لدينا إذن هذه الصورة لآلة شاملة
machinery in our heads
الاستعمال في رؤوسنا
in addition to this surprising array
إضافة إلى بعض نظام مفاجئ
of very specialized components.
لمكونات في غاية التخصص.
It's early days in this enterprise.
لا زلنا في البداية.
We've painted only the first brushstrokes
نحن رسمنا ضربات الفرشاة الأولى فقط
in our neural portrait of the human mind.
في لوحتنا العصبية للعقل البشري.
The most fundamental questions remain unanswered.
لكن الأسئلة الأساسية تبقى دون جواب.
So for example, what does each of these regions do exactly?
مثلا، ما وظيفة هذه المناطق بالتحديد؟
Why do we need three face areas
لماذا نحتاج ثلاثة مناطق دماغية للوجه
and three place areas,
وثلاثة أخرى للمكان
and what's the division of labor between them?
وكيف تنقسم الوظائف بينها؟
Second, how are all these things
ثانيا، كيف هي مرتبطة ببعضها
connected in the brain?
البعض في الدماغ؟
With diffusion imaging,
عبر اعتماد تقنية التصوير
you can trace bundles of neurons
يمكننا رصد حزم من الخلايا العصبية
that connect to different parts of the brain,
تربط أجزاء مختلفة من الدماغ
and with this method shown here,
من خلال هذا الأسلوب
you can trace the connections of individual neurons in the brain,
يمكنك كشف الروابط بين كل الخلايا العصبية في الدماغ
potentially someday giving us a wiring diagram
ممّا قد يمكننا في المستقبل من رسم تخطيط
of the entire human brain.
للدماغ البشري كاملا.
Third, how does all of this
ثالثا، كيف تتشكّل هذه الهيكلة
very systematic structure get built,
النظامية جدا أثناء
both over development in childhood
نمو في مرحلة الطفولة
and over the evolution of our species?
والتطور في نوعنا البشري؟
To address questions like that,
لمواجهة أسئلة مماثلة،
scientists are now scanning
يقوم العلماء الآن بتصوير
other species of animals,
أنواع حيوانية أخرى
and they're also scanning human infants.
وأيضا أطفال البشر.
Many people justify the high cost of neuroscience research
العديد يبرّر ارتفاع تكاليف أبحاث علم الأعصاب
by pointing out that it may help us someday
من خلال الإشارة إلى ما قد نستفيد منها في المستقبل
to treat brain disorders like Alzheimer's and autism.
في علاج أمراض دماغية كالزهايمر والتوحّد.
That's a hugely important goal,
إنّه هدف مهم جدّا،
and I'd be thrilled if any of my work contributed to it,
وسأكون سعيدة لو ساهم أي من أعمالي في ذلك
but fixing things that are broken in the world
لكن إصلاح أمور معطوبة في العالم
is not the only thing that's worth doing.
ليس الأمر الوحيد الذي يستحق القيام به.
The effort to understand the human mind and brain
جهود محاولة العقل البشري والدماغ
is worthwhile even if it never led to the treatment
مجدية حتّى لو لم تساهم في علاج
of a single disease.
أي مرض.
What could be more thrilling
ما الممتع أكثر من
than to understand the fundamental mechanisms
فهم الآليات الأساسية
that underlie human experience,
التي تقوم عليها التجربة البشرية،
to understand, in essence, who we are?
وفهم جوهر ما نحن عليه؟
This is, I think, the greatest scientific quest
هذا حسب رأيي أعظم سعي علميّ
of all time.
على الإطلاق.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)